<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Bounded Rationality (Posts about calculus)</title><link>http://bjlkeng.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/categories/calculus.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 23:37:40 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Lagrange Multipliers</title><link>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/lagrange-multipliers/</link><dc:creator>Brian Keng</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is going to be about finding the maxima or minima of a function
subject to some constraints.  This is usually introduced in a multivariate
calculus course, unfortunately (or fortunately?) I never got the chance to take
a multivariate calculus course that covered this topic.  In my undergraduate class, computer
engineers only took three half year engineering calculus courses, and the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ucalendar.uwaterloo.ca/1617/COURSE/course-ECE.html#ECE206"&gt;fourth one&lt;/a&gt;
(for electrical engineers) seems to have covered other basic multivariate
calculus topics such as all the various theorems such as Green's, Gauss', Stokes' (I
could be wrong though, I never did take that course!).  You know what I always imagined Newton
saying, "It's never too late to learn multivariate calculus!".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that vein, this post will discuss one widely used method for finding optima
subject to constraints: Lagrange multipliers.  The concepts
behind it are actually quite intuitive once we come up with the right analogue
in physical reality, so as usual we'll start there.  We'll work through some
problems and hopefully by the end of this post, this topic won't seem as
mysterious anymore &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/lagrange-multipliers/#id3" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/lagrange-multipliers/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (11 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>calculus</category><category>lagrange multipliers</category><category>mathjax</category><guid>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/lagrange-multipliers/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 12:48:31 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>