<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Bounded Rationality (Posts about CIFAR10)</title><link>http://bjlkeng.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/categories/cifar10.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2020 01:23:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>PixelCNN</title><link>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/pixelcnn/</link><dc:creator>Brian Keng</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's been a long time coming but I'm finally getting this post out!  I read
this paper a couple of years ago and wanted to really understand it because it
was state of the art at the time (still pretty close even now).  As usual
though, once I started down the variational autoencoder line of posts, there
was always &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt; another VAE paper to look into so I never got around to
looking at this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is all about a proper probabilistic generative model called Pixel
Convolutional Neural Networks or PixelCNN.  It was originally proposed
as a side contribution of Pixel Recurrent Neural Networks in [1] and later
expanded upon in [2,3] (and I'm sure many other papers).  The real cool thing
about it is that it's (a) probabilistic, and (b) autoregressive.  It's still
counter-intuitive to me that you can generate images one pixel at at time, but
I'm jumping ahead of myself here.  We'll go over some background material, the
method, and my painstaking attempts at an implementation (and what I learned
from it).  Let's get started!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/pixelcnn/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (23 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>autoregressive</category><category>CIFAR10</category><category>generative models</category><category>mathjax</category><guid>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/pixelcnn/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 11:11:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Importance Sampling and Estimating Marginal Likelihood in Variational Autoencoders</title><link>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/importance-sampling-and-estimating-marginal-likelihood-in-variational-autoencoders/</link><dc:creator>Brian Keng</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;It took a while but I'm back!  This post is kind of a digression (which seems
to happen a lot) along my journey of learning more about probabilistic
generative models.  There's so much in ML that you can't help learning a lot
of random things along the way.  That's why it's interesting, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today's topic is &lt;em&gt;importance sampling&lt;/em&gt;.  It's a really old idea that you may
have learned in a statistics class (I didn't) but somehow is useful in deep learning,
what's old is new right?  How this is relevant to the discussion is that when
we have a large latent variable model (e.g. a variational
autoencoder), we want to be able to efficiently estimate the marginal likelihood
given data.  The marginal likelihood is kind of taken for granted in the
experiments of some VAE papers when comparing different models.  I was curious
how it was actually computed and it took me down this rabbit hole.  Turns out
it's actually pretty interesting!  As usual, I'll have a mix of background
material, examples, math and code to build some intuition around this topic.
Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/importance-sampling-and-estimating-marginal-likelihood-in-variational-autoencoders/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (22 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>autoencoders</category><category>autoregressive</category><category>CIFAR10</category><category>generative models</category><category>importance sampling</category><category>mathjax</category><category>MNIST</category><category>Monte Carlo</category><category>variational calculus</category><guid>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/importance-sampling-and-estimating-marginal-likelihood-in-variational-autoencoders/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 12:20:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Label Refinery: A Softer Approach</title><link>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/label-refinery/</link><dc:creator>Brian Keng</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is going to be about a really simple idea that is surprisingly effective
from a paper by Bagherinezhad et al. called &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.02641"&gt;Label Refinery: Improving ImageNet
Classification through Label Progression&lt;/a&gt;.
The title pretty much says it all but I'll also discuss some intuition and show
some experiments on the CIFAR10 and SVHN datasets.  The idea is both simple and
surprising, my favourite kind of idea!  Let's take a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/label-refinery/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (10 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>CIFAR10</category><category>label refinery</category><category>mathjax</category><category>residual networks</category><category>svhn</category><guid>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/label-refinery/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2018 11:26:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Residual Networks</title><link>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/residual-networks/</link><dc:creator>Brian Keng</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taking a small break from some of the heavier math, I thought I'd write a post
(aka learn more about) a very popular neural network architecture called
Residual Networks aka ResNet.  This architecture is being very widely used
because it's so simple yet so powerful at the same time.  The architecture's
performance is due its ability to add hundreds of layers (talk about deep
learning!) without degrading performance or adding difficulty to training.  I
really like these types of robust advances where it doesn't require fiddling
with all sorts of hyper-parameters to make it work.  Anyways, I'll introduce
the idea and show an implementation of ResNet on a few runs of a variational
autoencoder that I put together on the CIFAR10 dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/residual-networks/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (9 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>autoencoders</category><category>CIFAR10</category><category>mathjax</category><category>residual networks</category><category>ResNet</category><guid>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/residual-networks/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2018 18:55:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Variational Autoencoders with Inverse Autoregressive Flows</title><link>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/variational-autoencoders-with-inverse-autoregressive-flows/</link><dc:creator>Brian Keng</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this post, I'm going to be describing a really cool idea about how
to improve variational autoencoders using inverse autoregressive
flows.  The main idea is that we can generate more powerful posterior
distributions compared to a more basic isotropic Gaussian by applying a
series of invertible transformations.  This, in theory, will allow
your variational autoencoder to fit better by concentrating the
stochastic samples around a closer approximation to the true
posterior.  The math works out so nicely while the results are kind of
marginal &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/variational-autoencoders-with-inverse-autoregressive-flows/#id3" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;.  As usual, I'll go through some intuition, some math,
and have an implementation with few experiments I ran.  Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/variational-autoencoders-with-inverse-autoregressive-flows/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (18 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>autoencoders</category><category>autoregressive</category><category>CIFAR10</category><category>generative models</category><category>Kullback-Leibler</category><category>MADE</category><category>mathjax</category><category>MNIST</category><category>variational calculus</category><guid>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/variational-autoencoders-with-inverse-autoregressive-flows/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 13:47:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Semi-supervised Learning with Variational Autoencoders</title><link>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/semi-supervised-learning-with-variational-autoencoders/</link><dc:creator>Brian Keng</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this post, I'll be continuing on this variational autoencoder (VAE) line of
exploration
(previous posts: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/variational-autoencoders/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/a-variational-autoencoder-on-the-svnh-dataset/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) by
writing about how to use variational autoencoders to do semi-supervised
learning.  In particular, I'll be explaining the technique used in
"Semi-supervised Learning with Deep Generative Models" by Kingma et al.
I'll be digging into the math (hopefully being more explicit than the paper),
giving a bit more background on the variational lower bound, as well as
my usual attempt at giving some more intuition.
I've also put some notebooks on Github that compare the VAE methods
with others such as PCA, CNNs, and pre-trained models.  Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/semi-supervised-learning-with-variational-autoencoders/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (25 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>autoencoders</category><category>CIFAR10</category><category>CNN</category><category>generative models</category><category>inception</category><category>Kullback-Leibler</category><category>mathjax</category><category>PCA</category><category>semi-supervised learning</category><category>variational calculus</category><guid>http://bjlkeng.github.io/posts/semi-supervised-learning-with-variational-autoencoders/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 12:40:47 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>